DERIN K JOSEPH

Full Stack Software Engineer 847-322-9793 derinbino@gmail.com U.S citizen

I am a Software Engineer living in the DFW area, Texas. I have experience in developing Full Stack applications using Java, JavaScript, Spring Boot, React, HTML5, CSS3, AWS, ES6, jQuery, Git, GitHub, Jira, Gitbash, AJAX, APIs, REST, Postman, Cloud Foundry, Spring MVC, Java Web, Spring Framework, Microservice, Back End, Junit Testing, Jest Testing, Spring Security, Web Services, User Experience, Jenkins, Docker, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Node, NPM, Maven, Gradle, Figma, Developer Tools, Adobe XD, Wordpress Etc.

I have a good understanding of SQL and NoSQL databases and have used it in multiple ways to identify solutions in very short duration. I have completed many user stories in an agile development process along with multiple defect requests.

While working at State Farm I have worked in a team with minimum viable product in mind but always went above and beyond with any extra time. I am involved in developing major enhancements in my current position with State Farm. In my daily work I utilized tools like JUnit to record various unit test cases and used a test-driven development approach. I love learning new technologies and have been actively learning Angular, Android application development and IOS development. I am a quick learner, good communicator and a team player.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: JAVA, JavaScript, Python

Frameworks: React, Ember, Spring MVC, Spring, Spring Boot

Web Services: AWS, Google cloud

Web Technologies: XML, CSS, Java Script, HTML, AJAX, API

Operating Systems: Windows 10, MAC OS, Linux **Databases:** My SQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB

IDE: Eclipse, IntelliJ, VS code, Sublime Text, Atom, PyCharm

Build Tools: Maven, Gradle

CI/CD Tools: Jenkins

SDLC Methodologies: Agile, Waterfall

EDUCATION

Liberty University: Online – B.S in Information Technology: Web and Mobile Development. Coursework: Software development, Networking, Database management, Internet architecture. Planned year of graduation is 2021.

North Lake College: Irving, TX – Web Production(development) and Design.

Coursework: Web Design Technology, Advance Program Concepts, Web Server Software, Web programming.

Tech Talent South Dallas, TX – Java Full Stack Development.

Coursework: Core Java, Databases, Spring, Spring Boot, Agile methodologies.

Tech Talent South Dallas, TX – JavaScript Application Development.

Coursework: Core JavaScript, JQuery, API, React, Redux, Node.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Software Development Engineer II

Employer: State Farm April 2020 – Present

- Used JSP for UI development.
- Developed backends for multiple applications using Spring framework.
- · Utilized Spring Boot for building services and business logic.
- · Unit tested all the code that was written using Junit 5.
- · Version controlled software using GitLab.
- Developed Restful APIs that communicate with the UI.
- · Used a PostgreSQL database, passing data from UI to DB and other way around.
- Used Jenkins for DevOps.
- · Pair programming and mob programming was utilized as needed.
- · Took responsibility in finishing stories and meeting business requirements on time.
- · Helped other members on the team to the best of my ability.

Technologies: Spring, Spring boot, Jenkins, PostgreSQL, Restful API, Postman, GitLab.

Software Development Engineer

Employer: State Farm August 2019 – March 2020

- · Used React and Ember for UI frameworks
- · Developed backends for multiple applications using Spring framework.
- Utilized Spring Boot for building services and business logic.
- · Unit tested all the code that was written using Junit 5.
- · Version controlled software using GitLab.
- · Helped develop Restful APIs that communicate with the UI.
- · Learned and used a company specific library for front end development.
- · Used a PostgreSQL database, passing data from UI to DB and other way around.
- Developed a Spring Boot project that can look at Java code and populate the DB.

- · Pair programming and mob programming was utilized as needed.
- · Took responsibility in finishing stories and meeting business requirements on time.

Technologies: Spring, Spring boot, React, Ember, PostgreSQL, Restful API, Postman, GitLab.

Web Developer Intern

Employer: Keep Dallas Beautiful (Dallas, TX)

Nov 2018 – June 2019

- Used HTML 5 and CSS for UI modifications.
- · Developed Several templates to give the client choices.
- · Once the template was chosen it was made into a functional prototype.
- · Me and my team worked on transferring relevant data to the prototype
- · Usability, UI and Business Requirements were the main focus.
- · Team collaboration and pair programming was a huge part of this project.
- · Took leadership role in given tasks and delivered everything on time.

Technologies: HTML 5, CSS 3, WordPress, Photoshop.

JAVA Development Trainee

Employer: Tech Talent South (Dallas, TX)

April 2019 - July 2019

- · Developed a web application that mimics twitter.
- Used Different Frontend and backend technologies in developing the application.
- · Used Spring Boot Framework and implemented Integration with Hibernate.
- · Worked using Agile methodology.
- · Developed Web page using HTML, Bootstrap, CSS and J Query.
- · Used Eclipse to build the code.
- · Used JUnit for testing the code.

Technologies: Core Java, Hibernate, Spring MVC, Spring Boot, HTML, Bootstrap.

JavaScript Development Trainee

Client: N/A

Employer: Tech Talent South(Dallas, TX,)

Feb 2019 - April 2019

- Developer an application that lets the user get their current address in case of emergency.
- · Developed application using open maps API.
- · Developed UI interface using HTML, Java Script, React, NodeJS, CSS, and J Query.
- · Used ES6 to make the application future proof.
- Worked on code management activities with GitHub for version control.

Technologies: Core JavaScript, XML, ES6, React, HTML, CSS.